<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anapausis. Rest for the restlesse soule. By Archibald Symmer, minister of the gospell</title>
            <author>Symmer, Archibald.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23586</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841754</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841754</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 718:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anapausis. Rest for the restlesse soule. By Archibald Symmer, minister of the gospell</title>
                  <author>Symmer, Archibald.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Haviland for William Sheres,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An exhortation to come unto Christ.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>At end: Imprimatur, Tho: Wykes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6357:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:6357:1"/>
ΑΝΑΠΑΥΣΙΣ REST FOR THE Reſtleſſe Soule.</p>
            <p>By ARCHIBALD SYMMER, Miniſter of the Goſpell.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATTH. 11. 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Come unto mee all yee that labour, and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Haviland</hi> for WILLIAM SHERES, 1637.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6357:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6357:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL Sir <hi>Iohn Hanbury,</hi> of Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marſh Knight, peace externall, internall, ſupernall, eternall.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFULL,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Reat is the love of Chriſt to his <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 16.</note> Saints, and gracious is the effect thereof in them, which is their Chriſtian charity one to another. This is not in word neither in tongue onely, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 18.</note> in deed, and in truth: and ſuch is that of your Worſhip to mee. This is a comfort; but what ſhall I ſay? it inferres a difficulty, it muſt bee mutuall, love requires a requitall, and how can <hi>Cleanthes</hi> requite a reall, a golden love with the airie ſtore of his phantaſie? For po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty is the patrimony of the Muſes. Noble
<pb facs="tcp:6357:3"/>
Sir, though <hi>Momus</hi> reckon, that letters are but the clouds of <hi>Helicon,</hi> yet in <hi>Apolloes</hi> eſteeme they are durable riches: yea ſo lovely is learning, and gracious are the Muſes, that <note place="margin">Favin. Pariſien. in his Theatr. Honor.</note> the Roſe is become their livery, and the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglyphick of ſuch as love them; and good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for moſt tried is the truth of that poſie: <hi>Dignum laude virum Muſa vetat mori:</hi> For Th' Immortal Siſters Chaplets in their bowers, They wither not, as doe all other flowers.</p>
            <p>Reject not therefore (I humbly intreat) this poore preſent of my ruſtick muſe, the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my love; ſo ſhall my little infant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſwadled in the gentle bands of your most worthy acceptance, batten at the laſt among men, and its parent ſhall be bound to continue,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips humble Orator at the Throne of Grace, ever in the Lord Jeſus to be commanded,</hi> Archibald Symmer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6357:3"/>
            <head>Comfort for a weary ſoule humbled for ſinne.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> All men are weary.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An that is borne of a woman, is of ſhort continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and full of trouble:</hi> Surely every childe <note place="margin">Job. 14. 1.</note> of <hi>Adam</hi> is altogether vanity: for all that is under the Sunne is vanitie, and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 11.</note> of the ſpirit; Which the wiſe man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares by his owne example, and very <note place="margin">Ecleſ. 1. 14.</note> deare experience. And if that wiſe and peaceable King of the Lords peculiar people, and glorious type of Chriſt the <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 1.</note> Prince of peace, and author of our hopes and happineſſe, <note place="margin">Pſal. 39. 5.</note> was on the higheſt ſpheare and top of all his earthly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and reſt, altogether vanity, what ſhall wee ſay of <note place="margin">Epict.</note> our ſelves, who are but punies, and Wretches, yea mappes of miſeries and calamities, in compariſon of him?</p>
               <p>Now this univerſall labour of mans mind, and unreſiſted vexation of his ſpirit, is properly when wee can neither obtaine that which wee deſire, nor ſhun that which wee loath. And as the mutinous perturbations and affections of our hearts and wils, and the deſires of our fleſh are in number and variety many, ſo are the afflictions and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſpirit; for every affection a ſeverall affliction. Every carnall deſire cauſeth ſorrow, &amp; ſorrow is a tedious labour and toyle to the mind, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15. 13. Every carnall
<pb facs="tcp:6357:4"/>
affection cauſeth griefe, becauſe it is alwayes confounded and diſappointed. What if the carnall heart obtaine all that it deſires? yet is it fruſtrated, and diſappointed ſtill; for it hoped for more comfort in its periſhing hopes and earthly tranſitories than ever they can poſſibly afford: the hope of earthly comforts is better than the fruition and injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them. Thus every man labours, is heavy laden <note place="margin">The labour of the unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</note> and weary under the burthen of vanity. The proud and ambitious man labours for honour and glory, and curryes the applauſe of the world with all his might, to touch hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, like <hi>Herod,</hi> with his finger, and the firmament, as <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimachus,</hi> with the point of his lance, and all is vanity. The mammoniſt and idolatrous worldling covets to wax plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 5. Col. 3. 5. Mammon in the Syriack di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alect is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of riches.</note> and rich; this is the moiling toile of his miſerable carkeis by day, and watching vexation of his reſtleſſe ſpirit by night. This labour is never at an end in this life: for mammon increaſeth as faſt as money, the love of riches in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth with the vanity loved: The Epicure and voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man labours for pleaſure, and to plunge himſelfe with the ſow in the mire of ſenſuality, and periſhing delight.</p>
               <p>This is the moſt brutiſh labour of all: for hereby a man <note place="margin">Creſcit amor nummi, &amp;c. Iuven.</note> is, as it were, metamorphozed and turned into a beaſt. The envious man labours to annoy and endammage his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: Thus did thoſe forty men travell with miſchiefe, that vowed <hi>Pauls</hi> death: their labour was painfull; for they would neither eat nor drink, till they had effected their purpoſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus all men labour by nature, and all are weary, and all theſe labours are ſinfull.</p>
               <p>The Saints and ſpirituall Ones of the Lord alſo labour, but after another manner; theirs is a bleſſed labour, for it is for the remiſſion of ſinnes, and peace of conſcience: they are weary under the burthen of Iniquity, and therefore cry out every one with <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 51. 2. Waſh mee through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from mine iniquity, and cleanſe mee from my ſinne; and with the holy Apoſtle, O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver mee from the body of this death?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:6357:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> All finde not reſt.</head>
               <p>ALl our cares tend to this end (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">No true reſt for the wicked.</note> that wee may enjoy the thing wee deſire. And the heart findeth reſt when it obtaines that which it hopeth and labours for. Now Chriſt will never fulfill any carnall deſire, therefore the naturall and carnall heart ſhall never finde content and reſt; there is none for ſuch in Chriſt, for <note place="margin">Caſſiodor. Pſalm. 6. A narrow ſea betweene the haven Aulis of Beotia and Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baea, Ariſt. Iſa. 57. 21.</note> carnall men are none of his, whom nothing can pleaſe but the new creature, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 15. For they have not the Spirit of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. And without Chriſt there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but labour and toile, vexation and wearineſſe. The world is like an Iriſh ſea, wherein is nothing to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but the ſtormy tempeſts of adverſity. It is like Euripus, which ebbeth and floweth ſeven times a day, conſtant onely in inconſtancy. Behold therefore the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall mans folly, though there be no peace to the wicked, ſaith my God; yet will hee ſeeke for content and reſt by the meanes of his owne labour, and to quiet his diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented heart by his owne wayes, but all is in vaine. Riches cannot poſſibly ſatisfie the covetous man; if <hi>Jupiter</hi> (as the heathen reporteth) ſhould multiply his ſheepe ſtill at his requeſt, hee would mutter notwithſtanding: <hi>Pauperis eſt numerare pecus,</hi> hee is but a poore man that can number his flock. The Epicure and ſenſuall man thinketh to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the concupiſcence and luſts of his fleſh, by obeying and following the ſame, but hee is groſſely deceived: for as oyle being caſt into the ſea mitigates the violent ſurges of the ſame, but for a moment, and by and by they become a great deale fiercer: ſo the thing that a voluptuous man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, though it abate the toile of his labouring minde, it is but for a while, and never fully, but preſently afterward it befalleth him as it did the monſter <hi>Hydra;</hi> when <hi>Hercules</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Simile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6357:5"/>
had cut off one head, two did riſe in the place, ſo the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures labour, and vexation of his ſwiniſh heart, after it is a little mitigated, increaſeth, and ariſeth to an higher pitch than ever it did afore. As then he that hath the dropſie can never quench his thirſt by drinking, ſo can no carnall and unregenerate man content and quiet his ſpirit with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of this world, nor the ſenſuall ſoule its brutiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire with pleaſures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> All and onely the weary members of Chriſt are refreſhed.</head>
               <p>HO, every one that thirſteth come yee to the waters, &amp;c. for thus ſaith hee that is high and excellent, hee <note place="margin">Iſay 55. 1.</note> that inhabiteth the eternity, whoſe name is the holy one. I dwell in the high and holy place, and with him that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to give life to them that are of a contrite heart, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57. 15. And againe, Come unto me all ye that labour <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 28.</note> and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt. Such as feele the burthen of their ſinnes originall and actuall, and grone under the ſame, labouring to have the releaſe and eaſe of <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 3.</note> them, and ſuch as are poore in ſpirit, and ſenſible of their ſpirituall wants and weakneſſe, lowly in heart, and baſe in their owne eſteeme, and therefore labour for the free par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all their offences for the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 9.</note> Chriſt, which is by faith, and a joyfull ſenſe of the love and favour of God, which is better than life it ſelfe, and pray for that peace of God, even that tranquillity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that paſſeth all naturall underſtanding; ſuch as are thus humbled, are fit objects of mercy and compaſſion: <note place="margin">C. 4. 7.</note> for the Lord giveth grace unto the humble: they are capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of reſt and refreſhment. Such broken hearts are the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices <note place="margin">Iam. 4. 6. Pſal. 51. 17.</note> of God; a broken and a contrite heart, O Lord, thou
<pb facs="tcp:6357:5"/>
wilt never deſpiſe; who ſo doth pray with <hi>David, hide thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">V. 9, 10, 11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>face from my ſinnes, and blot out all mine iniquities: Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in mee a cleane heart, O God, and renue a right ſpirit within mee; Caſt me not away from thy face, and take not thy holy ſpirit from me: Reſtore unto mee the joy of thy ſalvation, &amp;c.</hi> that poore ſoule ſhall be liberally comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and fully refreſhed in the bowels of Chriſts endleſſe compaſſions. Never did any Faithfull penitent heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the throne of Grace without ſome ſenſible con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation. Never did Chriſt ſince the foundations of the <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.</note> world, reject any of his poore ranſomed members; but though their ſinnes were as red as crimſon, they became as white as ſnow, ſo that the bones which the Lord had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, did ever thereafter rejoyce in his mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The reaſon of the former point.</head>
               <p>ALl the weary Saints of Chriſt are refreſhed, whether <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 28. Eph. 6. 9.</note> theſe be rich or poore, Jewes or Greeks, bond or free, mals or female: for with God there is no reſpect of perſons, but as many as walke according to this rule, peace ſhall be upon them, and mercy, and upon the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God. Who <note place="margin">Gal 6. 16.</note> elſe ſhould be invited unto the participation of mercy, to be partakers of the privileges and comforts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 8, 9.</note> of Chriſt, but ſuch as he came into the world to ſave? whom ſhould he refreſh, but thoſe whom he hath redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? <note place="margin">Matth. 10. 6.</note> And whom ſhould hee exalt, but thoſe for whoſe ſakes he was humbled, and afterward highly exalted? Now it is evident that Chriſt was ſent of the Father into the world, <hi>not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance, and to ſave the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> for the ſame was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of him, by the holy Ghoſt, long before his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And when Chriſt himſelfe came to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth,</hi> where he had beene brought up, he went (as his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb facs="tcp:6357:6"/>
was) into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and the booke of this Prophecie being delivered of the Miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <note place="margin">Luke 4.</note> him, he expounded the ſame: The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, becauſe he hath anoynted me, that I ſhould preach the Goſpell to the poore: hee hath ſent mee, that I ſhould heale the broken hearted, that I ſhould preach deliverance to the captives, and recovering of ſight to the blind, that I ſhould ſet at liberty them that are bruiſed, and that I ſhould preach the acceptable yeere of the Lord, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 16, 17, 18, 19. Hence it is evident, that our bleſſed Saviour was ſent of God the Father not for his owne cauſe, but for his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted members ſake, neither came he to be Lord over all, but to redeeme all his owne. So God the Father delivered <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 27.</note> all things unto him, he gave him all power both in heaven, and in earth, &amp; made him Lord over all; that hee might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver <note place="margin">C. 28. 18.</note> us, wretched ſoules, from the jawes of hell, and pull us out of the pawes of that infernall Lion Satan, whoſe bondſlaves we were, ſitting in darkneſſe, &amp; in the region and ſhadow of death, till that day-ſpring from on high viſited <note place="margin">Iſay 9. 1. Luke 1.</note> us, and ſet us at libertie. Thus our bleſſed Redeemer ſitteth at the right hand of God, and maketh interceſſion for us, he helpeth his afflicted ſervants, and ſends them releaſe in <note place="margin">Rom. 8 34. Gen. 45. 5.</note> their diſtreſſes. So was <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſent into Egypt by God, and there exalted for the preſervation of his Church, and ſo he was a type of Chriſt. So <hi>David</hi> was preferred, and advanced <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> unto the Kingdome of Iſrael, and ſo was hee likewiſe a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Damnable is the caſe of all ſuch as are ſtrangers from Chriſt.</head>
               <p>WHat ſhall wee ſay then of thoſe that are enemies unto the Croſſe of Chriſt Jeſus? what is the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> of ſuch as are ſtrangers from the life of God, aliens from the common wealth of Iſrael, and forrainers from the Covenants of promiſe, who have hope, but are without
<pb facs="tcp:6357:6"/>
God in the world, walking according to the courſe of the ſame, according to the Prince of the power of the aire, the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience? Their eſtate is moſt damnable &amp; wofull; the tragicall plight of all ſuch impenitent and ſenſeleſſe ſinners is to be deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red even with teares of bloud. The Atheiſt, that is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and diſobedient, and unto good works reprobate, though his cauterized conſcience, and ſenſeleſſe heart har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened through the cuſtome and habit of ſinne, ſeeme to reſt and ſleepe for a while; yet ſhall hee be awakened with a <note place="margin">The miſery of the Atheiſt.</note> dolefull wakening, when the dreadfull ſenſe of the wrath of the Lord of hoſts ſhall laſh and whip him naked, as hee did <hi>Cain,</hi> and as the furies of hell did monſtrous <hi>Nero.</hi> Then ſhall he cry out with curſed <hi>Caligula:</hi> A wounded conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <note place="margin">Gen. 4. Sueton. in Ner.</note> who can beare it? Where ſhall he reſt then? all his former pleaſing courſes then ſhall he condemne, as <hi>Job</hi> did his friends: miſerable comforters are ye all, <hi>Job.</hi> 16. 1. Thus <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 14.</note> is the wicked like the raging ſea that cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt up mire &amp; dirt, <hi>there is no peace to the wicked,</hi> ſaith my God, <hi>Iſay</hi> 57. 20, 21. The proud Phariſee and Juſtici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie Hypocrite, that flatters and deludes his ſoule with a groundleſſe opinion of his owne righteouſneſſe, ſhall in ſtead of peace and reſt inherit trouble and ſorrow: for all his righteouſneſſe is <hi>inſtar panni menſtruati,</hi> like a filthie <note place="margin">Of the proud Phariſee.</note> clout, <hi>Iſay</hi> 64. 6. and therefore when <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> hungry man, after his dreame, <hi>Iſay</hi> 29. 8. and Paſſets, the Juglers gueſts ſhall be ſatisfied, &amp; filled with the phantaſticall ſhewes, and vaine appearances of imaginary and vaniſhing diſhes; then ſhall the hypocrites heart be quieted and refreſhed through <note place="margin">Iſay. 29 8.</note> his owne righteouſneſſe: for his moſt plauſible workes of morality, and ſeeming devotion, are ſo imperfect, &amp; pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <note place="margin">Jewel.</note> that they are not able to abide the examination of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovaes</hi> all-ſeeing eye, and triall of his dreadfull tribunall: none but that pure and perfect righteouſneſſe of Chriſt can endure it: none but the contrite heart, that is clothed and armed therewith, ſhall ever bee able to ſtand before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6357:7"/>
If ſuch ſmooth formaliſts finde no true reſt, what ſhall <note place="margin">Of thoſe that ſeeke for helpe of wizzards &amp;c.</note> we ſay then of ſuch as ſeeke for comfort and eaſe, not through any appearance of goodneſſe, or ſo much as any ſhew of holineſſe; but by the meanes of the devill, as wiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, and witches? cold is their comfort: it is like a draught of cold water to a man that is ſick of the dropſie; as that haſteneth him to his grave, ſo doth this diabolicall comfort drive the Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> to the pit of hell. What fruit reaped <hi>Saul</hi> by his conference and conſultation with the witch at <hi>Endor,</hi> and with the devill himſelfe? A wofull anſwer: <hi>Tomorrow ſhalt thou and thy Sonnes be with mee, &amp; the Lord ſhall give the hoſt of Iſrael into the hand of the Philiſtines.</hi> And what was the effect of this anſwer? Surely nothing but bitter feare, and fainting infirmity, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28. 20. <hi>Ahaz</hi> died the death becauſe he ſent to enquire of <hi>Baalzebub</hi> the devill, god of <hi>Ekron,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 3. 4. Thus are all the enemies of Chriſt, and ſuch as are ſtrangers from him, ever confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> An Exhortation to come unto Chriſt.</head>
               <p>WHoſoever then would find reſt unto his weary ſoule, muſt come unto Chriſt: for hee is that Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28. <hi>Chriſtus ſcala coeli.</hi>
                  </note> which <hi>Jacob</hi> in the way to <hi>Haron,</hi> ſaw reaching to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, whereby God and man are joyned together, and by whom the Angels miniſter unto us: all graces, joyes, and reſt by him are given unto us, and we by him aſcend into heaven, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. 12, 13. Neither is there ſalvation in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for among men there is given none other name under heaven, whereby wee muſt be ſaved, <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 12. And this is our glorious prerogative, and conſolation, that if any man ſinne, Jeſus Chriſt the juſt is our Advocate with the Father, and he the atonement for all our ſins. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 1, 2. For the office of his interceſſion and redemption are joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:6357:7"/>
together. And howſoever he prove a ſtumbling block to the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and fooliſhneſſe unto the <hi>Grecians:</hi> yet unto them which are called, both of <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Grecians,</hi> Chriſt <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 23 14</note> is the power of God, and the wiſedome of God, yea hee is all in all, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 11. Hee is our hope, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 1.</p>
               <p>Without Chriſt then, and the grace of his Kingdome, there is nothing in the world but vanity and vexation of ſpirit. Learning, and victory, plenty, and pleaſure, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and length of dayes, vanity of vanities, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt all is vanity. As <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> learning increaſed, ſo did the care and toyle of his reſtleſſe &amp; wandring ſpirit, ever till the firſt borne of death had the dominion over him. As <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Quint. Curt. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us Pellaeo Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veni non ſufficit orbis, &amp;c. Iuven.</hi> Sat. 10.</note> was the maſter, ſo was his Scholler. <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, when he had conquered and ſubdued <hi>Grecia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> all theſe triumphant victories could not content his unſatiable heart, but he wiſhes that Phlegra field had beene full of Giants, like <hi>Porus,</hi> that moſt magnanimous and mightie Indian Prince, to fight withall, and that the vaſt Ocean had beene firme land. There is no earthly materiall thing that can ſatisfie the heaven-borne, immateriall ſoule, none but that infinite God of ſpirits is able to content <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 7.</note> mans unſatiable ſpirit. For the Lord made it for himſelfe, to feed on his immortall joyes and dainties: <hi>Plutarch</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore derides and mocks the Epicure and ſenſuall man, that would delight and pleaſe the ſoule with the pleaſures of the body. This is impoſſible: Let the Ruffian labour to drowne his melancholy fit, and cheare up, and refreſh his penſive and languiſhing heart, with quaffing, and ſwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and healthing; yet ſhall he be confounded; drink may make him mad, but never truly merry; he may roare, but never rejoyce, for this is the privilege of the ſober Saints of Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 11. Be glad in the Lord, rejoyce ye righteous, and ſhout for joy, all yee that are upright in heart. But ſome man will object, What? did not the noble <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> and brave Philoſophers, and learned of the Gentiles, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> (who called, as it is reported, and brought as it were
<pb facs="tcp:6357:8"/>
Philoſophy downe from Heaven) and divine <hi>Plato,</hi> who taught the Art of prayer, and wiſe <hi>Seneca,</hi> who wrote ſo <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Alcib.</hi> 2. <hi>vel de voto. Null. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund, Plutar.</hi>
                  </note> learnedly of the tranquillitie, and peace of the mind, &amp;c. Did they never attaine unto true bleſſedneſſe and reſt? Surely no: for though they ſought and ſearched for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation and peace to their troubled minds; yet did they never labour for this peace of God, which paſſeth all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall underſtanding, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 7. For they knew it not, and why? Becauſe they knew not <hi>Christ,</hi> the Lord of glory and peace, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 8. So without Chriſt the way unto peace, they wandered out of the path of peace, without Chriſt the Truth of peace, they obtained at the moſt but <note place="margin">Iohn 14. 6.</note> a ſhadow of peace, as <hi>Ixion</hi> embraced an empty cloud in ſtead of his beloved <hi>Juno,</hi> and without Chriſt the life of peace, they ended their lives, and their peace together. Wherefore, if any man would live in peace and joy with God and his owne conſcience, which is Gods continuall Deputie, he muſt begin, continue, and end in Chriſt. No beginning of true peace, till a man begin truly to live in Chriſt; and no continuance and perpetuity of reſt, unleſſe <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 25.</note> hee continue and reſt in that God of reſt. If after wee are received in the ſheepfold of that Shepheard, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of our ſoules, wee goe aſtray at any time, and paſſe beyond the limits and bounds of his bleſſed will, then doe wee diſquiet and trouble our ſoules; wee refuſe <note place="margin">Iſay 8. 6.</note> the waters of <hi>Shiloah,</hi> that runne ſoftly, and ſweetly, and goe to the ſwelling and raging waters of <hi>Jordan.</hi> What trouble and ſorrow, and bitter anguiſh of heart did poore <hi>David</hi> ſuffer by the meanes of his ſinnes? how heavy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and lamentations did he expreſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. 25. 32. And how ſtrong teares and prayers ſent he up to the Lord againe for mercy and forgiveneſſe, and for the renewing of his holy Spirit of peace, and joy in him? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. So doth every ſanctified ſenſible ſoule feele the ſmart of ſinne, and breach of peace by the ſame. When God is offended, the conſcience is troubled; and till he be pacified, peace
<pb facs="tcp:6357:8"/>
cannot bee recovered. Therefore the wounded ſoule muſt runne unto Chriſt, and reſt in him.</p>
               <p>Now the man that commeth unto Chriſt for mercy <note place="margin">How we ſhould come unto Chriſt.</note> and peace, hee muſt run unto his Redeemer, with the two ſpirituall feet of faith and repentance; of faith, becauſe it is impoſſible without faith to pleaſe God: for he that commeth to God, muſt beleeve that God is, and that hee is a rewarder of them that ſeeke him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11. 6. And he that asketh and beggeth of Chriſt what he needeth, muſt aske in faith, and not waver: For hee that wavereth, is like a wave of the Sea, toſſed of the wind, and carried away. Neither let that man that doubteth of Gods will, thinke that he ſhall receive any thing of the Lord, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 6. 7. He muſt runne likewiſe with the foot of Repentance: For wee know that God heareth not impenitent ſinners, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of God, and ſuch as delight in wickedneſſe, <hi>John</hi> 9. 31. Which that bleſſed man, after Gods owne heart, confeſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66. 18. If I regard wickedneſſe in mine heart, the Lord will not heare mee. Hee that commeth unto Chriſt to bee comforted and exalted, muſt firſt bee <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 14.</note> humble and dejected, and in the humiliation and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of his heart enter in at the ſtrait gate, and walke in the narrow way that leadeth unto life: For the man that is ſtuffed up with ſinne, and puffed up with pride and arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, with luſt and covetouſneſſe, with a naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of righteouſneſſe, with malice and envy, &amp;c. ſuch a one is too too big to enter in at that ſtrait gate, and walke in <note place="margin">Matt 7. 13.</note> that narrow way; he can no more get in and walke there, than a Camell can goe through the eye of a needle. But the contrite and broken heart, the ſoule ſorrowfull for ſinne entreth in at that gate, and walketh in that narrow way, which leadeth it aſſuredly unto ſolid and true reſt. The <note place="margin">Jer. 6. 16.</note> true penitent is conducted and led unto true reſt, and his joy is certaine: For Chriſt promiſeth the ſame aſſuredly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 28. <hi>Refocillabo vos,</hi> I will give you reſt. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth more than any corporall Phyſician dare, or can
<pb facs="tcp:6357:9"/>
doe to his patient: he can but offer his paines, and promiſe to doe his beſt endevour; but he cannot promiſe recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of health to the ſicke: But Chriſt doth infallibly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure his ſpirituall patient of true health, and peace to his ſoule. Never was there from the foundations of the world, any contrite ſpirit diſappointed of this joyfull refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor ever ſhall be. A broken and a contrite heart, O God, thou wilt never deſpiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 17. Chriſt the God of truth hath ever fulfilled his promiſe. And as this reſt is certaine, ſo is it ſolid and true: the remiſſion of ſins, the ſenſe of Gods love, and the peace of conſcience, is heaven upon earth: is it a continuall Feaſt, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a chearfull countenance, and cauſeth good health, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. 22. yea it ſuſtaineth and beareth the infirmities, and all the croſſes, and vexations of this life, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18. 14. <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 13.</note> And finally, being the firſt fruits, and beginning of eternall bliſſe, it is the infallible note and token of the ſame. Who ſo findeth, and enjoyeth this reſt, the ſame ſhall be glorified after this life with Chriſt in the heavens world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Wykes.</signed>
               <dateline>Lond. <date>Oct. 10. 1637.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6357:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
